he came back from the injury and made
improvements it wasn't just recovery
from injury to get back to where he was
he's continued to progress despite his
injury it took one competition it took
the New York Pro for me to say Nick
Walker is now a Podium threat at the
2024 Olympia the Adaptive athletes have
reinvented the game in a way to figure
out what those movement patterns are
with the way that they have to adapt to
get to these heavy weights that it
becomes a whole new it's like seeing the
sport in a whole new light regularly
testing one rep Max's Hooper recommends
doing this every 6 to 12 weeks I think a
lot of lifters don't do it that
often hey folks welcome to strength
weekly the weekly YouTube show that
brings you everything you need to know
from around the barbell game Phil
Blackman and I are both on the road this
week in different parts of the country
but that won't stop us from bringing you
the latest and greatest from the barbell
game and also the stones game and also
because you know it's not just barbells
we cover a lot anyway we have a barbell
bias let's put it that way Phil speaking
of barbell bias we have four great
stories to cover this week let's give
the rundown Nick Walker qualifies again
for the Olympia after an injury kept him
out from last year he is looking pretty
darn in shape is he an Olympia Contender
after winning the New York Pro Karen
Anderson sets a new equip squat world
record at 279 kilos we talk about that
and why even with that world record she
actually wasn't able to crack the
overall podium in her equipped
powerlifting competition kind of an
interesting story there we dive into
that adapter strongman James spurgen
showcases his strength with a 570 lb
deadlift triple also squatted that for a
triple we talk about Spur's interesting
and very accomplished career in strength
Sports and why maybe we should be paying
more attention to Adaptive strength
Sports especially adapted strongman but
maybe that's just because I particularly
like that we have some bias here we like
to show that and and fourth 2023 world
strongest man and reigning Arnold
strongman classic Champion Mitchell
Hooper talks about breaking through
plateaus and give some really actionable
advice you know we love to uh dive into
the training here and the science behind
this because we don't want you just to
know what's going on with strong people
we want you to get stronger or at least
equip you to get stronger anyway well
Phil um let's not beat around the bush
let's get into it what did what did Nick
Walker do give us give us the rundown
and okay first off let's talk about Nick
Walker season last year what happened to
Nick Walker last year Phil so Nick
Walker was a contender going into the Mr
Olympia everybody thought that he had a
shot to win the overall title it is felt
as though for his career he's very young
still that over the course of his career
he is an inevitable Mr Olympia that's
just the the err apparent in the sport
that eventually Walker will claim the
title that's how it felt that's how it's
been that's the trajectory he's been on
his whole career even though he's still
relatively young and then he has a
hamstring injury that Sidelines him from
the 2023 Olympia even though he was on
the trajectory to it like be a Podium
Contender he was the Bronze medalist the
year before uh he had only moved upward
from fifth to Third and then it was
expected that maybe he could contend for
the throne and then a hamstring injury
uh like within the week of uh when the
Olympia supposed to happen Sidelines him
and it was tragic you could see that he
had already he had been uh prepping for
a while when he made the announcement of
his hamstring injury he was already
leaned out he was ready to compete and
it was sort of a heartbreaking moment to
see somebody who was at one of the top
contenders not be able to compete fans
were upset we were upset wanting to
cover because we like covering Nick and
then the story then became what is it
going to be like when he recovers from
his injury this New York Pro was his
return from that hamstring injury and he
smashes it he's now a two-time New York
Pro and that qualifies him back for the
Olympia now one thing that like wasn't
really talked about all that much was he
was supposed to go into the Olympia and
then he got a hamstring injury he got
injured and he didn't want a special
invite to come back into the Olympia
because he never actually like competed
on the invitation that he had previously
for being the bronze medalist when he
podiumed the year before in 2022 he had
the invite for that Podium to come back
in 20123 and then he he didn't want a
special invite he didn't want special
treat he wanted to earn his way back and
I mean to talk about a hero's journey
he's now made his way back he's now a
two-time New York Pro we like because of
of that we did full live coverage of the
New York Pro which is not something that
we've done for the this level of event
before but it was enough of a story that
we felt that it was warranted and he
came back and he smashed it he beat
Martin Fitzwater who was already
qualified for the Olympia for having won
a previous show this season and he beat
Tonio Burton who was the defending New
York Pro Champion those guys were the
three on the podium in that order and
for Nick to come back in this way after
the injury when there was a lot of talk
of what is this going to look like how
is he G to recover he recovered in
remarkable fashion this is this is
really a stellar performance and I want
to point out that after prejudging he
was only one point ahead of Martin but I
will say at the end of the show the kind
of uh anecdotal let's call it on social
media you know the armchair pundits
would say that Walker almost certainly
brought by far the best package to Stage
like that that the margin of Victory it
was close coming out of prejudging was
maybe you know he looked better than
maybe the margin of Victory implied
after that form of judging um again
that's all anecdotal that's just based
on you know what folks were saying but
Nick Walker is back let's put it this
way right like Nick Walker won that
competition this wasn't a sympathy win
right this wasn't like you talk about
the hero's journey Nick Walker earned
that he brought a great package to Stage
he looked super well conditioned his
midsection like the definition in his
midsection right which has never been
really a problem for Nick Walker was
absurd absolutely absurd he brought a
fantastic package to Stage like there's
a little controversy or at least again
this is something it's talked about on
social media um we are not Nick Walker's
Physicians right like it is not up to
our place to really judge but there's
been some concern because of uh what
looked like varico veins in his legs
there's been concerns like like Health
long-term health concerns again it's
very easy for us to sit back and just
like say that doesn't look healthy right
we don't really know right we're not
Physicians we're not Nick Walker's
Physicians we're not like working with
him on a day-to-day basis but that has
been a concern over Nick Walker's career
and it's kind of followed him I don't
know if that's like fair or not
basically because it's not has nothing
to do with his muscularity it has
nothing to do right with what the judges
are are really looking for so I just
want to point that out it's something
always follows him it feels kind of
silly to not address it because every
time we post anything about Nick Walker
especially on YouTube the comment
section comes out in full force
ultimately like I I think the judges
have to take out of their they you know
they can't really factor that in because
it's not a component of the judging but
look I thought the package I wasn't
covering it live all weekend I kind of
saw the Recaps I saw it on social media
I saw some of the footage later on Phil
you know I thought Nick Walker very much
earned this Victory the New York Pro is
one of the Hallmark competitions in
bodybuilding maybe we should cover it
live all the time because it is truly a
storyed event he becomes one of the few
multi-time winners of the New York Pro
one of the Premier qualification events
for the Olympia yeah Nick Walker I gotta
be honest it took one competition it
took the New York Pro for me to say Nick
Walker is now a Podium threat at the
2024 Olympia right up there uh with
hotti shupin right up there with Derrick
Lunsford right like I think Nick Samson
dauda like I think you got to put Nick
Walker back in the conversation we
weren't really sure where he was I think
now the podium the podium conversation
is kind of a fourman chat right
now yeah and to continue on that thought
that you just made about uh about Nick's
legs is even though it's not in the
judging parameters the bodybuilders
genetics have always been an influence
on how somebody looks aesthetically and
how that has to be judged so yeah it is
something that they we can't we can't
not discuss because it is part of the
deal but it is not part of the judging
parameters per se but it is something to
to keep in mind like when you're
watching how how he poses with his body
because every athlete has to present
their body in the best possible light
and I'm Nick must be aware of how and
obviously about how to best pose his
body and it's been successful for him so
far the thing that I want to point out
about this uh particular performance and
like you were talking about about how
conditioned he came in and how tit his
midsection looked Is Not only was this
performance indicative of okay he has
recovered sufficiently from his injury
to get back to the elite level but he
made he came back up from that injury
and made improvements it wasn't just
recovery from injury to get back to
where he was he's continued to progress
despite his injury and I think that's
really where like you see that kind of
elite professionalism because he wasn't
it wasn't just I need to get back to
form it is I need to come back better
despite the injury so I have to both
recover and get better and he did both
and it resulted in a goal that the New
York BR Phil you always bring up the
considerations that I am too much of a
simpleton to really understand so I
always appreciate that you are the yin
to my yang the Yang to my Yen but really
you are the commentator who keeps me in
line so I really do appreciate that
let's let's move on to the sport of
powerlifting Karen Anderson setting a
new equi squat record at 279 kilos Phil
can you give us a little bit of context
on her performance and what that means
because she is in powerlifting years
relatively young has only been competing
for a couple of years yeah so here's her
rundown she only started powerlifting in
2021 and three years later she's already
hitting in the 84 kilogram class she's
scoring a 279 kilogram squat now that is
obviously huge she uh competed equipped
so it's an equipped squat uh record so
she was using single ply equipment so
those are the parameters of what the
squat was ipf equipped right multiply
just to be clear folks when we say
equipped ipf equipped it's single ply
there are a lot of different federations
there's multiply liting we ain't talking
about that right here this is ipf you
got to walk that bar out ain't no
monolift and it's single ply
equipment and uh for for all the people
watching we know there are inid
federations there are in so we're
covering our bases it's the iPad okay so
uh even though she scored this this
incredible squat the big story also
attached to this huge lift is the fact
that it didn't get her onto the podium
now she got fourth which is still pretty
good but the reason that she didn't get
on the podium and this is why this story
was so fun fun is she's so early on in
her powerlifting Journey but she's
clearly at the elite level to be scoring
these kinds of lifts but you can still
see that there are areas that she has to
progress because the the thing that held
her back was in her bench press she
capped out at 110 kilograms now if
you're competing at 84 kilos you need to
be scoring higher than that unless you
have like a remarkable Squat and a
remarkable bench now she's got a
remarkable squat her deadlift was able
to get her back into fourth place but
her bench press is what held her back so
it's it's going to be really fun to
watch the continuing trajectory of this
young powerlifting athlete because she's
incredible on the squat and we know that
and now we're going to be watching for
every time she puts the bar bar on her
shoulders before she tries to squat it
out but we're going to see can she
improve her bench press to actually
start scoring some podiums and if she
can then you know now we're going to be
in gold medal contention for every
competition that she enters she's only
been competing in power thing for about
three years a little less than three
years actually I believe the thing about
power and she's a relatively young
athlete she just recently aged out of
the Juniors out of the junior division
in powerlifting uh which is where she
made her debut I want to point out that
in powerlifting there are a few factors
bench is is a the bench press in
competitive powerlifting is a lift that
tends to mature more slowly over time
getting more year you know I was once
talking to Kevin Oak who is a world
record holding powerlifter and he's like
listen the lift that kind of links
powerlifters and bodybuilders is the
bench press because both just take
muscle maturity right it takes years to
build the mass and to build the
musculature that's going to move the Ben
bench press and you know we talk about
training the movement as opposed to
training the muscle the bench press is
kind of like a synthesis of those two
things right and especially in equipped
powerlifting where it's so incredibly
highly technical now equipped
powerlifting is technical in every
component every lift but there's a
technical element and there's simply
just a training though the muscles
involved in that movement pattern
element that takes years right so we do
see younger lifters they might come out
hot and they might develop really
impressive squats and really impressive
deadlifts very quickly the bench press
especially for women who just carry less
muscle mass in their upper bodies
naturally it takes a while to build that
maturity in the bench press right so we
do see a lot of younger lifters or
lifters earlier in their powerlifting
careers that are squatting and
deadlifting in the elite ranks but it
literally takes years to build muscle
maturity in the bench press I talked to
Jen I've talked to Jen Thompson you know
one of the powerlifting goats uh when it
comes to especially raw powerlifting
perhaps the best raw bench presser of
all time in powerlifting and you know
she's like I didn't really hit my stride
in the bench press until my mid 40s you
know and so it just takes time right so
when we say that this is like a weakness
for Karen or a weakness for any
lifter it's it's not so much a criticism
as it is just an observation and
something that is fairly common among
young powerlifters when they age out of
Juniors into you know the open
division their bench presses just often
lack beh lag behind because it takes
years to add kilos to to that lift could
be in the Raw division or it could be in
the equi division where it's so
incredibly technical to use that
equipment just an observation I always
love an excuse to talk about some of the
nerdier aspects of powerlifting Phil
let's move on to some more nerdy aspects
of strength Sports James spurgen he's an
Adaptive strongman but he's actually
competed across multiple strength
categories so um before we get into what
James did recently give us a quick
rundown of who James spurgen is and why
we should care so James spurgen is is a
an Adaptive strongman he is trained uh
he has trained with big laws Lawrence
Shai former 20 uh he's the who was the
2016 Europe strongest man we know big
laws lawen Shai he's a big name in the
in the strongman space he's retired from
competitive strong man but he's still in
the game as a commentator and such and
he coaches many athletes including not
only spurgen but also he worked with
Mitchell Hooper before so big names uh
so spurgen is an Adaptive strongman uh
he lost use of his right arm after an a
motorcycle accident back in 2006 the
reason that we're covering him is
because we saw him do a 570 lb triple
recently a one-armed deadlift
effectively with 570 pounds for a triple
now that is massive for anybody not just
an Adaptive athlete like we would cover
that regardless so that is was an
impressive feat in its own right and of
course that gets uh hopefully that gets
everybody who's watching this and
everybody who is not aware of James
Bergen yet to do a deeper dive into what
he has accomplished thus far in his
adapter strongman career and adapter
strongman in general because there are a
lot of very very very strong athletes in
that field of competition and barbend is
also going to to start covering that
more acutely we're going to be diving
more into the adapter strongman space
because there are lot there are a lot of
impressive athletes that are doing
things that would be impressive whether
they were adaptive or not and are that
it is worthy of our attention in ways
where it's like if you like big lifts
then James Bergen is obviously somebody
to keep an eye on yeah and the
interesting thing about this is you know
it's it's a one-arm it's a one-arm
deadlift um there is like a there's a
strap involved and it's it's best to
just watch the lift which we're going to
be showing in this broadcast right as to
how exactly spur in his technique it's
it's quite interesting um I also want to
say he also squatted this weight for a
triple and I want to point out um
because it's something that I've seen on
social media on some of his his list
like oh a squat how does you know lack
of use of one arm impact your squat
think of when you're squatting
heavyweight on a back squat right not
being able to use both your arms means
it's much more difficult much more
difficult to secure and stabilize that
barbell right it takes Cor strength and
it takes proception and it takes
stability in a way to do that with
without the use of an arm in a way that
is just above and beyond and inherently
more challenging than if you are able to
use both arms in an equal fashion to
secure a barbell in a back spot so I
just want to point out that spurgen
showing pretty darn Elite strength he's
an athlete who's competed in a in
multiple adaptive strength Sports I want
to point out strongman is kind of what
he's best known for now I'm going to
read out some of his uh accomplishments
in adaptive strongman over the last
eight years he was the 2016 America's
strongest adaptive athlete second place
2017 Arnold strongest disabled man fifth
place standing division same in 2017
fifth place in the standing division at
America's strongest disabled man 2019
static monsters first place 2020 static
monsters first place and 2020 world's
strongest disabled man first place
standing C2 division so it's been a
little bit since we've seen him kind of
compete at the elite level but I think
what spurgen is showcasing here is that
he's looking stronger than ever
potentially and I am excited to see him
I'm excited to see him hit some
competition soon we don't actually know
the next time he's planning on competing
I don't believe he is also the world
record holder in the one-arm partial
deadlift which he set in 2020 with 675
pounds pretty excited to see spurgen
back and again spurgen is one of those
athletes who's been around adaptive
strength competition for quite a while
and this isn't like a an official record
this is a triple and training but we're
going to start covering more adaptive
strength Athletics including uh adaptive
strongman so uh you know I think spurgen
definitely an athlete to watch and uh
expect more of this on the broadcast
yeah one thing that I I am have looked
forward to now that we have the capacity
to start covering more adapter strongly
in competitions is one of my favorite
ideas in strength Sports in general is
that uh bodybuilding trains muscles and
strong man trains movements and for to
to go into adaptive strongman and see
how they have to adapt how they're
training movements in order to
accomplish these kinds of massive
weights it becomes a a whole it just
opens a whole new light on anybody who
has followed strength sports for any
amount of time and respects the uh the
ability of what these athletes can do
and the training that is involved to get
to that point the Adaptive athletes have
that but they are like have reinvented
the game in a way to figure out what
those movement patterns are with the way
that they have to adapt to get to these
heavy weights that it becomes a whole
new it's like seeing the sport in a
whole new light that is still familiar
and I I find to be just both like
intellectually stimulating as also very
exciting to watch well intellectually
stimulating and exciting and that's why
we do what we do Phil we're going to
move on to another big name in the
strong man Community 2023 world
Strongest Man Mitchell Hooper and
reigning arold strongman classic
Champion Mitchell Hooper same person I
don't know why I said that twice
recently posted a video he posted a lot
of good content he's a smart guy he's
got a research a clinical background as
well in physiology uh and and movement
patterns worked with in private practice
as well he's not just a competitive
athlete he brought up six tips for
breaking through plateaus a lot of them
borrowing from his personal experience
and I thought this was a really fun one
to highlight today because we often
cover news here on strength weekly but
it's also good I think to cover when we
spot something that is just so relevant
that it makes us go oh my goodness
that's really useful hey let's leave
folks with a few tips that will help
their own training not just just uh
aspirational lifts from Top athletes uh
Phil if you want to kick us off we'll
alternate what is the first tip Hooper
had for busting through plateaus so the
first step that he has is periodization
now we've heard of what periodization is
before if you've watched uh any of
strength weekly before we have discussed
it in the past or if you've uh come over
to barban to see any of the uh training
articles that we've covered
periodization is something that comes up
uh fairly often and it is he recommends
that maintaining the same weight
deliberately deliberately but slowing
down the a or what also might be known
as Tempo training that can help bust
through a plateau uh keeping the weight
constant but intentionally enhancing the
speed or explosiveness through each rep
that can help you break through a
plateau using the same weight but adding
an extra rep or adding an extra set that
can help break through a plateau so
there's all these different metrics that
you can adjust without having to change
the actual load itself that can help
bust through a plateau if that's where
you're at and but part of that can also
be informed by the next one right and
when it comes to I mean when it comes to
plos maybe the most annoying thing in
strength train because you're putting
all the work in and you're not making
progress well Hooper reminds us to
actually reference our plateaus with
periodic testing what is actually your
one rep max sometimes we think we might
be in a training Plateau but we actually
don't have a good reference for where
our strength is where it's progressing
or not progressing so regularly testing
one rep Maxes Hooper recommends doing
this every 6 to 12 weeks I think a lot
of lifters don't do it that often right
we're just like oh this is my one rep
max and then you think of like oh you
think I've been referencing that as my
one rep max for a year where is it where
am I actually now am I not actually
plateaued but is are signals different
signals of progress not indicating
progress like they used to uh or they
not indicating strength ends like they
used to but maybe actually my one rep
max has gone up maybe it's gone down
actually testing your one rep maxes at a
relatively regular Cadence important
there Phil what is the next tip and
that's I mean off of that point is
knowledge is power right if you act if
you have the most up and relevant
information about where your strength is
that can remove any mental gaps that are
in the way and having a strong mindset
about how to progress through a plateau
uh can also be extremely helpful we have
we have a lot of research that has shown
that visualization and other mental
factors when it comes to lifting heavy
can make a difference in the quality of
your lifts and the and how heavy you can
go and the confidence with which you
approach a lift so exceeding your mental
limits is Hooper tip for number three
but a lot of that comes from knowledge
is power if you know what your one rep
max is and then you approach a barbell
and that's within your range you might
attack it a lot better than you would if
you didn't know that information so
being able to exceed those mental limits
is tip number three something that can
also help with your uh your mindset when
it comes to lifting in the gym is his
next tip all right tip number four this
is an important one train with strong
people right it that kind of goes into
tip number three about the mentality
right Hooper references like when he
started training in a specific like
strength Focus gym and not just a
commercial gym his strength went up
because he's training around people who
actually pushing themselves who are
training for strength right get specific
with your training environment could be
your training Partners or just people
you're training around it's going to be
a big mindset shift and it's going to
help you get a more accurate reference
maybe more aspirational reference for
what's actually possible in your own
training Phil Fifth and final tip that
Hooper gave I think I let intro this
with six tips but it's really just five
apologies folks come at me in the
comments I can't count that well Phil
what's the Fifth and final tip the fifth
and final tip is one that is you know
across any sport across any type of
strength training that you have it's
staying consistent if you want to see
progress over time you have to stay
consistent with your training regimen
and all of the other tips that we just
mentioned like those you you have to be
on your game with those or try best to
be on your game with those but most
importantly you have to stay consistent
even if you're not hitting the numbers
that you think you are even if you're in
a plateau staying consistent through
that regardless of where your numbers
might be is important to actually break
through well consistency is key and
that's why we are bringing strength weak
this week even though Phil and I are on
the road for strength weekly I'm David
Thomas to joined by Phil Blackman
folks take a second slow down appreciate
life think about your own training how
to bust through plateaus personally
strengthwise emotionally socially reach
out to those friends you haven't talked
to in a while bust through friendship
plateaus until next time thanks for
joining us
[Music]